Guide to the Stanford University, Institute of American History, Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Institute of American History, records
1938-1973
SC0162
Stanford University. Institute of American History
6.25 Linear feet
The administrative records include correspondence predating the Institute's official founding, correspondence regarding THE CRISIS OF THE UNION (1966), manuscripts of articles, publications, materials relating to conferences, workshops, committees, special scholarships, the Coe fellowships, and other Institute activities.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer, History Department: Institute of American History, 1977.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
The Institute was founded in 1942 by Professor Edgar E. Robinson and the Stanford History Department to examine current conceptions of American History, and current methods of presenting American History in the schools, colleges and university.
Description of the Collection
The administrative records include correspondence predating the Institute's official founding, correspondence regarding THE CRISIS OF THE UNION (1966), manuscripts of articles, publications, materials relating to conferences, workshops, committees, special scholarships, the Coe fellowships, and other Institute activities.
Access Terms
Robinson, Edgar E.; Robinson, Edgar E.; Stanford University. Coe Fellowships.; Stanford University. Department of History.; Stanford University. Institute of American History; Toynbee, Arnold,, 1889-1975.; Toynbee, Arnold.
Collection Contents
- Records, Accession ARCH-1994-005
  - "Historical Bases of Americanism" - note cards, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Interpreting American History (E. E. Robinson) - typescript (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Hystory Syllabi - E. E. RAobinson (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Seminar 330, 8/16/55 - notes from, book lists (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Misc. Syllabi, book reviews (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Scholarship and Cataclysm (E. E. Robinson) - typescript, correspondence, etc. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - White House Library list, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Adjustment of the College Curriculum to Wartime Conditions and Needs," 1943 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (largely of E. E. Robinson), 1944 - 46 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - History Courses in Junior College & College (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Inst. of Amer. History - Misc. pubs., memos (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Misc. Items re. Teaching History (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Misc. Syllabi (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - NY Times Survey on Teaching of U.S. History in Colleges, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Sources: "News of the Nation" (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Stanford Conf. of Ca. College and Univ. Teachers of American History, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Survey on the 11th Year Social Studies (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Clippings and Publications (Box 2)
  - Clippings and Publications (Box 3)